Task number 39.
This task is a Prolog task,
but I'm going to solve it first in Haskell
because it is easier to understand.
We're going to write predicate g
which, when interpreted as a function,
inserts some specific element between each
two adjacent elements of the given list.
So, for example, this should hold.
As you can see, at the beginning we had this list
[b,a,d], and then after the insertion of “a” between
each two elements… ,so you could say like: each
of these commas is replaced by: comma a comma.
You can imagine it like this.
And this should hold. So,
this should give us true.
Now I'm going to show you some examples. So,
what would happen if we do this as a function
in Haskell instead of a predicate in Prolog?
This function, after we write it somehow,
then we go and use it. We do g and we give it
one parameter ‘x’ as a character and
another parameter “abcd” as a String,
and it should give us this String.
As you can see, it inserted x
in between each two elements.
But as you can see here, we have
two parameters while here we have
three (what do you call them?)
three clauses for g in Prolog,
because, as we agreed before, if you have this g
and you want to write it as a Haskell function,
it's going to correspond to
a function g that takes this and this as
parameters and then it results in this.
But as a predicate, it's just going to
take these three clauses and give you
either true or false. (Just a reminder)
Now, a second example. Now, instead of
having one character and then a list
of characters which is a String, now we
have one Integer and a list of Integers.
And as you can see, this is the
result that we want to have. This is what our
function should give us when we write this.
And now what about basic cases?
So, for example, if we have an
empty list, then of course we
should get an empty list no matter what
the element is, because, as we said here,
the task wants us to have the function…
I mean the predicate or, if I
write it as a function in Haskell…
So, the task wants us to have it to
insert this element in between each
two elements of the list, and here we
don't even have any elements at all.
And now, the same goes for this list… for
any list that contains only one element
because how are you going to insert
an element between just one element?
It doesn't make any sense at all. So, these
two here, they look like they are base cases.
So, if you're going to write this function
and use recursion, these two cases are going
to be the base cases, the empty list
and the list that contains one element.
Why? It's just because of the nature of
the task. This task is talking about
inserting things between two elements
and not just doing something to one
element at least or something like that.
So, the nature of the task requires
us to deal with two elements at least.
This means these two things here
are two separate base cases.
Now, let's go back to Prolog. I'm going to
show you the same four examples from here.
And there is really not much difference except for
that g here is a predicate and it just tells us
True or False, and this g here is a function and
it results in some values. It gives us a list.
Now, I'm going to show you how to write g in
Haskell. And I'm going to do it the simple way.
Of course, I could make it as a function that
takes three parameters and returns a Boolean.
So now, we have a predicate
which is similar to this predicate. But no.
This is just too complicated. It will look
much more complicated than this
and it's not very useful for us.
So, I'm just going to make it the exact
same way that we learned in the lecture.
Now, instead of having a predicate
that has three clauses, we have a
function that has only two parameters.
And because Haskell has a type system, here
is the type signature of the function g.
And notice here that we didn't
specify. We just said: some type (a).
The element that we're going to insert
is just some element of any type.
And we have the parameter.
This list is going to be
a list of (a), and then we're
going to also get a list of (a).
Now, let's look at the function
and try to understand it.
As I said, here, these two are base cases.
If we have whatever element and we want to
insert it in an empty list, it just doesn't work.
We just get the empty list as it is. And the same
is true for a list that contains only one element.
We just get the same list as it is because
as I said before, the task wants us to
insert this element in between
each two elements of the list,
and here we don't have two elements.
We just have one. Here we have zero.
And now what happens if we have
the element x and we have the list that
starts with y and z and ends with z's?
This here is also a list
and these here are elements.
And what we get is a list that starts with
y and then it has x which is the element
that we want to insert, and then it has z which is
this element that used to be the second element.
Now it's third because we inserted x in between.
And now we have two cases… actually three
cases depending on this list of z's.
So, if this list is empty, this means that
this part here is trying to insert x into
an empty list… actually into a list that
starts with z and ends with the empty list,
which means, in total, this is a list
that contains only the element z.
So, what happens if you try to insert one
element into a list that contains one element?
Then we get this case. So, this here is going
to be just the list that contains z as it is.
And this would be a correct solution.
As you can see, this means, originally, we
had a list that had only y and z because
this is empty, and we just inserted x in between.
That's it. We are done.
And now what happens if this
list had just one element?
So, let's say this list has I don't know…
whatever. Let's say the Integer 1, or let's say 4.
So, this means, here, we are trying to insert x
into a list that contains one... two elements.
So, this here would be the list that
contains 4. And then, with this operator,
we get here, in total, a
list that contains z and 4.
So, z could be any other Integer. I don't know.
And what happens if you insert an element
x into a list that contains two elements?
Nothing special. It just gets inserted just like
the first case that I discussed a minute ago.
And if this still doesn't look clear
to you, I'm going to do an example.
Let's copy this and go somewhere here,
and let's do some manual evaluation.
I'm going to get these same examples.
Let's do it.
What is g of x and this String “abcd”?
Is this list empty? No. Does it have one
element? No. So, this means we are in this case.
So, now x would be the character x, y would be
the character a, and z would be the character b,
and z's would be the list that contains c and d.
And according to this, this should
give us the element y, which is a.
This is how I should write it because it's a
character. So, it should give us a, and then
x, and then the list that has g ‘x’.
And x in our case is the
character x. And here we have
the element z which is b. So, here we have b and
then we have the list z's which is in our case
“cd”.
Now let's continue with this.
So, here we have g of ‘x’ and this list.
This list is basically just this list.
And what happens if you try
to insert x in this list,
but now this time, y is b, and z is c, and z's
is the list that contains one element which is d?
So, let me copy it. So, we get: first the
element y which is b. And then we get x and then
g x, and the third element… actually
the second element was c. So, we get c.
Oops! So, we get c and the
list that contains just d.
But d is a String.
So, this here should be
one string “cd”, like this.
Here, this would be y, and this
is z, and the empty list is z’s.
So, this means what we get here
is c followed by x then g ‘x’...
And now finally, we are
going to use the second case.
So here, g is inserting the element x
into a list that contains one element.
And this means we only get the list as it is.
c, x and d.
As you can see, this is
the solution. It's correct.
Now let's look at the Prolog solution
and see how it's written in Prolog.
It is very similar, except for this
here. This here is a variable Us.
And we are saying that Us is the
result of inserting X into this list
which is exactly the same
as what we are doing here.
What we are saying here is that
the result should start with Y
and then X, and then the rest of this list is
going to be the result of inserting X into this
list which starts with Z and ends with Zs.
This here is exactly the same. So, we're saying
that the result should start with Y then X,
and then it ends with a list Us which
itself results from… (see? it's the
same). It's results from inserting X into the
list that starts with Z and ends with Zs.
And if you think about
this task intuitively,
maybe you would write something like this.
This would be your solution, maybe. So,
what does this solution mean? It says:
the empty list stays as it is.
We don't insert anything into a list
that contains one element; also the same.
But a list that contains two elements, we just
insert the element by putting it in between.
Otherwise, a list that contains
more than two elements,
then we do exactly the same as
here for the first two elements.
So, we had first element X, second element Y,
then we inserted A in between, and then we said:
the rest of the list results from inserting the
element in the list that used to be the rest,
but in addition to this element.
So, inserting the element into this list
that starts with Y and ends with Xs.
So, this solution is correct, but as you can see,
we're doing the exact same thing here and here.
So, this means there is redundancy, and this
is why it is better to write it this way.
And now there is actually another solution
I would like to show you, which is this.
What we're doing here is exactly the same
for the base cases, but the difference is
that here,
instead of having a list that starts with Y, Z
and then the rest is Zs, now we just have a list
with the head Y and the tail Ys,
and we are saying that Us, this time,
results from inserting X into the list Ys,
which used to be the tail of the original
list. And here we have to add this condition.
We have to say that Ys cannot be
empty. And if you solve it this way,
then you should be careful because this
here cannot be placed before this one.
So, you cannot do it like this.
This wouldn't work.
Now let me test the Haskell solution.
Let's reload.
And there is not really much
of a difference except for
that these here are predicates.
So, they have three things inside… three clauses.
And that's basically
it.
Great! It is working.
What happens if I change…? Let me change here.
So, it is working.